<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pleasures vision with deserts complaint, and a short dialogue of a womans properties, betweene an old man and a young. By Arthur Newman of the Middle Temple Gent</title>
            <author>Newman, Arthur.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848432</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1179:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pleasures vision with deserts complaint, and a short dialogue of a womans properties, betweene an old man and a young. By Arthur Newman of the Middle Temple Gent</title>
                  <author>Newman, Arthur.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] E[ld] for Thomas Bayly, and are to be sold at his shop in the Middle-row in Holbourne neere Staple Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:31"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:31"/>
            <p>PLEASVRES VISION: <hi>WITH</hi> DESERTS COMPLAINT, <hi>AND</hi> A SHORT DIALOGVE of a Womans Properties, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an old Man and</hi> a Young.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> ARTHVR NEWMAN of the <hi>Middle Temple</hi> Gent:</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G. E.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Bayly,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in the Middle-row in Holbourne neere Staple Inne. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND truely Worthy, Sir <hi>George Newman Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured this meane worke to your learned Cenſure, onely with a longing deſire to make my loue to you legible: and I was the more incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, in that I knew you would read with Patience; for I aſſure my ſelfe you will forget no Vertue. Yet ſince I expect for but a bewraying witneſſe of mine idle houres, ſo great a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as your graue Patronage, I muſt acknowledge my ſelfe guilty of inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable
<pb facs="tcp:13525:3"/>preſumption, that ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of my fault may plead for ſome fauour, although not altogether for pardon. I can ſay little for my ſelfe but this, that if I haue here done amiſſe, I promiſe all my endeuours for amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereafter. In the meane time I wiſh I had done better, and more for your ſake, then myne owne. For I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your worth, and account it a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to preſerue your Loue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Vnfainedly yours,</hi> ARTHVR NEVVMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:3"/>
            <head>AD AMICVM ſuum omni laude et ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruantia digniſſimum AR: NEWMAN.</head>
            <l>NOui tenerum, noui iuneuilibus annis</l>
            <l>cùm vox iucundi plena leporis erat,</l>
            <l>Et dixs de te mihi ſemper, Apolline cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>dignus eris: nec mens haec mihi vana fuit,</l>
            <l>Ecce Caballino ſitis eſt nunc fonte lenata:</l>
            <l>pocula Caſtali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s nunc ſaturantur aquis,</l>
            <l>Digna trophaea feres, cingent tua tempera la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t patria eſt meritis grata futura tuis.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>PE: LOWER.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:4"/>
            <head>PLEASVRES VISION.</head>
            <l>VVHen, in the Confines of the ſilent Night</l>
            <l>Refreſhing <hi>Sleep</hi> ſeiſd on each wearied wight</l>
            <l>And did, with gentle Slumbers, and ſoft Eaſe,</l>
            <l>The raging Motions of ſad Care appeaſe;</l>
            <l>Huſht were the moanes of haples wights oppreſt:</l>
            <l>And harmel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thoughts were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill'd in pleaſant Reſt:</l>
            <l>Now, bad, vnquiet, and pernitious mind.</l>
            <l>Surceaſd to plot their dangerous Deſignes:</l>
            <l>Now, ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll'd was Strife, and troubleſome Debate,</l>
            <l>And pining Enuy, now forgot to hate:</l>
            <l>And darkneſſe raign'd, that harmeles Sleepe might be</l>
            <l>Hid f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om the Troubles which the Light doth ſee:</l>
            <l>And, in the Bed whereon my ſelfe was laid,</l>
            <l>There, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou c Slumbers, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lodging ſtaid:</l>
            <l>But me of Reſt, deluding <hi>Marpheus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d;</l>
            <l>And, in a Dreame my Senſes ſo deceau'd</l>
            <l>That, as awak't, I ſaw, or ſeem'd to ſee:</l>
            <l>A perfect Man, or Gallant, one was he:</l>
            <l>But by the ſtrangenes of his outward ſhow</l>
            <l>He ſeem'd the laſt, and he was doubtles ſo.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>Light was his cariage, and his Gate affected,</l>
            <l>Oay his attire, and manly Shape neglected:</l>
            <l>For like a nice Dame that doth Pride affect,</l>
            <l>He with vnmanlike Curiouſneſſe was dect:</l>
            <l>In Nations of diſguiſes he was clad,</l>
            <l>And euery Limbe a ſeuerall faſhion had:</l>
            <l>And euer on himſelfe he fondly gas'd,</l>
            <l>As, with the ſtrangeneſſe of himſelfe amas'd:</l>
            <l>And on himſelfe enamoured was he,</l>
            <l>As commonly Fantaſtiques vſe to be.</l>
            <l>His vnpremeditated words, like wind</l>
            <l>Were light, and bluſtring, and bewraid his minde:</l>
            <l>Vnconſtant, and ſtill wandring were his lookes,</l>
            <l>And, in his face, as in laſciuious bookes</l>
            <l>Whole Stories you of lightneſſe might haue read;</l>
            <l>For there, it wantonly inhabited,</l>
            <l>Yet he, of Natures beſt guifts, plenty had:</l>
            <l>And pitty 'twas they were beſtow'd ſo bad,</l>
            <l>For thoſe ſaue Eyes which lewdnes ſo proclaim'd,</l>
            <l>Nature at firſt for ornament ordain'd:</l>
            <l>For ſhe had done her part, and ſet him forth,</l>
            <l>With liuely Shape, and outward ſignes of worth,</l>
            <l>And Hope at firſt ſaid, this faire ſeeming Inne</l>
            <l>Had no ill gueſts that harboured within.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:5"/>
            <l>His lightnes was not Natures fault, ô no,</l>
            <l>It was his mind that thoſe parts ſniut'd ſo:</l>
            <l>Then Nature, ſince thy bounty wrong'd hath beene,</l>
            <l>In ſuch againe let it no more be ſeene.</l>
            <l>His youthfull yeares did flowriſh in their prime;</l>
            <l>And luſty health, chear'd vp his lookes: and Time</l>
            <l>On his vntamed will did ſeeme t'attend,</l>
            <l>As though to him a Seruant, and a friend.</l>
            <l>Swift Time, that it might be by him well vs'd,</l>
            <l>Oft ſhew'd, that where it idly was abus'd,</l>
            <l>There it muſt vaniſh, and pe're come againe,</l>
            <l>But oft be call'd, and cride for backe, in vaine:</l>
            <l>And Fortune looking on him, ſmooth'd her Brow,</l>
            <l>And plai'd the Prodigall that he might know</l>
            <l>She hath no bounds to limit her great power,</l>
            <l>But where ſhe ſmiles, ſhe cloies; yet if ſhe lower,</l>
            <l>Then, acts a Miſery beyond beliefe:</l>
            <l>And as the fills with ioy, ſo kills with griefe.</l>
            <l>Then Beauties deckt with Nature, and with Art,</l>
            <l>Did all their ſweets to his deſires impart,</l>
            <l>They freely opened to compleate his pleaſure,</l>
            <l>Their all-alluring, and commanding treaſure.</l>
            <l>Some had ſuch tempting lookes, and Angell-features,</l>
            <l>That, but I ſaw their frailty, heauenly Creatures</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:6"/>
            <l>I them had deem'd: they power had to allure</l>
            <l>(Without great prouidence) holy, and pure.</l>
            <l>And ſure there is no man (as I belieue)</l>
            <l>That can behold ſuch erre but he muſt grieue.</l>
            <l>Others there were, and of an other kind</l>
            <l>Which alſo fancied his luſtfull mind.</l>
            <l>Some meanely faire, ſome foule, others their feature</l>
            <l>With Art did helpe, in ſpight, and ſcorne of Nature.</l>
            <l>With thoſe he wanton'd for variety;</l>
            <l>(For all, inſatiable Luſt muſt try.)</l>
            <l>Thus ſlept he in this Dreame of falſe delight,</l>
            <l>Still acting ſhamefull deeds, of ſhameles Night;</l>
            <l>And waſting Plenty, as with Spoyle compounded</l>
            <l>In lauiſhing, and all Exceſſe abounded:</l>
            <l>Banquets were Surfeits, and were nere without</l>
            <l>Healths of abuſed Wine ſtill quaft about.</l>
            <l>He in the ſpoyle of honeſt thrift did ſlow;</l>
            <l>And none (alas) ſaid, this ſhould not be ſo</l>
            <l>His Eares were ſlopt when was blam'd by Fame,</l>
            <l>And ſome to adde more fuell to his ſlame</l>
            <l>Falſly proteſted, pitty 'twas that he</l>
            <l>Might not ſome King, or mighty Monarch be:</l>
            <l>And to ſuch height his bounty did aduance,</l>
            <l>"That he to his owne muſicke ſeem'd to dance.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>None there diſtinguiſht Liberality</l>
            <l>From all-conſuming Prodigality:</l>
            <l>For pledges of their loue, they ſmooth words pawn'd,</l>
            <l>And iuſt like dirty dogges vpon him fawn'd,</l>
            <l>That leaue no loue ſigne but offen ſiue Mire.</l>
            <l>Others there were, to humor his deſire,</l>
            <l>That ſtill with new-found Sports his fancy fed,</l>
            <l>And him from pleaſure vnto pleaſure led,</l>
            <l>They had the Art, and onely trickes to ſtray</l>
            <l>With all deuiſes tending to decay.</l>
            <l>And, what he lik't, or loathed, none gainſaid,</l>
            <l>But good, or bad, his will was ſtill obaid,</l>
            <l>Baſe ſeruile minds euen ouer humor'd him,</l>
            <l>Whilſt he in Seas of fleeting ioyes did ſwim.</l>
            <l>The vncontrolled life he did commend,</l>
            <l>And deareſt deem'd his numor-feeding friend:</l>
            <l>And ſtill, Vice-puniſhing Authority,</l>
            <l>He, (outlaw-like) would ſlight; and brauing try</l>
            <l>Deſperate Exploits; to ſhew he nought did feare,</l>
            <l>Nor yet his humor could, or would forbeare.</l>
            <l>And ſuch as he was, were his company,</l>
            <l>That ready alwaies were for Villany.</l>
            <l>No care, or griefe did harbour neare his heart,</l>
            <l>No croſſe did from his Iollity him part.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>No want of Pleaſure, Liberty, or Faſe</l>
            <l>Did his contentments any way diſpleaſe;</l>
            <l>For, all delights which might each Senſe content,</l>
            <l>By Vanity her ſelfe to him were lent.</l>
            <l>But ah, extreames can ne're indure, and Meate</l>
            <l>That is moſt ſweet with ſowreſt Sauce we eate:</l>
            <l>For, in a moment all this vaniſhed,</l>
            <l>And he himſelfe ſtood ſtrangely altered:</l>
            <l>For, where as once he ſeem'd a blooming Spring,</l>
            <l>O're-filld with plenty of each pleaſing thing:</l>
            <l>Now feeble Age, and now diſdained want,</l>
            <l>Seem'd in his lookes their dwelling ſeates to plant.</l>
            <l>His Eies waxt hollow, lookes leane, cold his heates,</l>
            <l>And cate had folded vp his browes in pleates,</l>
            <l>He rent his haire, his face hee bath'd in teares,</l>
            <l>For pretious Time miſpent in youthfull yeares:</l>
            <l>And, as chiefe Cauſe of his miſery,</l>
            <l>On pleaſures paſt exclaimed bitterly:</l>
            <l>For calling them to mind, he ten times more</l>
            <l>Did execiate his Fortune, then before.</l>
            <l>Many paſt by, and laught his woes to ſcorne:</l>
            <l>And ſome did patty, ſeeing him for forlorne.</l>
            <l>Yet, former friends, but like his ſhaddow were</l>
            <l>That follow'd him in Sun-ſhine euery where;</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>But, when a Storme of Trouble commeth on,</l>
            <l>They ſoone fall off; and like to ſhades are gone:</l>
            <l>Yea, each thing elſe, that he eſteemed deare,</l>
            <l>But to augment his anguiſh did appeare.</l>
            <l>And, all the flatt'ring Hopes he erſt poſſeſt,</l>
            <l>Forſooke him quite, and he was quite diſtreſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe alterations ſeem'd to me ſo ſtrange,</l>
            <l>That I inquir'd the Cauſe of all this change.</l>
            <l>Whereat his heauy Eies on me he bent,</l>
            <l>Through ſtreames of Teares, made thick with languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</l>
            <l>And, bid me lend his words attentiue eare,</l>
            <l>That in my heart I might them better beare.</l>
            <l>I ſilent was; when, loe, this ruthfull Man,</l>
            <l>With Sighs, and Sobs his ſpeaches thus began.</l>
            <l>In prime of luſty head, when youthfull Spleene,</l>
            <l>Had ne're the wiles and guiles of Pleaſure ſeene.</l>
            <l>Not dreampt, how pretious is ſwift winged Time,</l>
            <l>Which, as it flees, our Fortunes fall, and climbe:</l>
            <l>Nor yet, by othe charmes once taking heed,</l>
            <l>But wild delights did wandring Senſes feed:</l>
            <l>Then, my vaine will vntam'd, vntutored,</l>
            <l>Left Reaſons Rule, and roau'd as fancy led:</l>
            <l>Like to a loſt Sheepe, from his Shepheard ſtraid,</l>
            <l>Running to wracke without his Keepers aid.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:8"/>
            <l>I ne're my owne affections did controule,</l>
            <l>For they commanded all within my Soule:</l>
            <l>Not I regarded future good, or ill,</l>
            <l>Nor had of Pleaſure till my fall, my fill.</l>
            <l>I did amiſſe; and now with griefe may ſay,</l>
            <l>Onely for that, I threw my ſelfe away:</l>
            <l>Yet blinded, no familiar dangers knew,</l>
            <l>That waited on me; nor till I did rew,</l>
            <l>Percen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d that woe on pleaſure did attend,</l>
            <l>Which contraries, (too oft) in one doe end.</l>
            <l>O! ſo my thoughts with pleaſures ſpells were charm'd,</l>
            <l>That they ore came me gainſt their force vnarm'd:</l>
            <l>For which, nought but Repentance yeelds reliefe,</l>
            <l>And yet (alas) that adds but griefe to griefe:</l>
            <l>Yet griefe for graceleſneſſe doth much relieue,</l>
            <l>Becauſe we ought for graceleſneſſe to grieue.</l>
            <l>Friends I obai'd not, therefore they me leaue,</l>
            <l>Pleaſure I follow'd, that did me deceaue:</l>
            <l>Fortune, and Time once gently on me ſmil'd,</l>
            <l>I then miſtaking both, my ſelfe beguild,</l>
            <l>I Time miſpent, and Fortune did neglect,</l>
            <l>Therefore with cauſe they doe me now reiect.</l>
            <l>I made the meanes, (for my good onely) lent,</l>
            <l>By lauiſhing, of woe the Inſtrument.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>And then braue Prodigall Vice ſtil'd my name,</l>
            <l>Now therefore, Ruine, and the Map of ſhame:</l>
            <l>And wherein I my ſelfe thought moſt ſecure,</l>
            <l>I'me therein for myne Error moſt vnſure.</l>
            <l>If man himſelfe can promiſe ought; 'tis this,</l>
            <l>That what he aimes at moſt, he moſt ſhall miſſe,</l>
            <l>For worldly certainty is but althought,</l>
            <l>And ſo it vaniſheth, and turnes to nought.</l>
            <l>O! of all Creatures breathing vitall Aire,</l>
            <l>Man, of his wauering fate may moſt deſpaire:</l>
            <l>For, there's no danger, miſery, nor Care,</l>
            <l>But therein deſtin'd is to him a ſhare.</l>
            <l>And his beſt earthly bliſſe no longer laſts,</l>
            <l>Then Vapors doe, in whirling windy blaſts:</l>
            <l>If rich, or poore, a Begger, or a King,</l>
            <l>His Roſe hath prickes, his honey hath a Sting:</l>
            <l>His comick-mirth is mixt with tragicke woes,</l>
            <l>And Ebbs inſue when moſt he ouerfloes:</l>
            <l>He like the Moone may not at full remaine,</l>
            <l>But (like her) changing ſtill, muſt wax, and waine;</l>
            <l>He, onely he, is nought but fortunes ſport,</l>
            <l>The ſpoyle of Time, and place where Cares reſort,</l>
            <l>The plant that 'midſt great heate, and moiſture grow'th,</l>
            <l>Now greene, now parcht, now at a ſtay, 'twixt both.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:41"/>
            <l>The very wheele which Fortune turneth ſtill</l>
            <l>Is Man; for him ſhe turnes which way ſhe will:</l>
            <l>He ſeemes of Change a Character, or Map;</l>
            <l>Or what is ſtill moſt ſubiect to miſhap.</l>
            <l>Or like a Ship, whoſe Pilot wanting skill,</l>
            <l>(Though far from Rockes) in doubt, and danger ſtill:</l>
            <l>For here and there the Fortunes of Man kind,</l>
            <l>Are blowne, and toſt like Ships in ſtorming wind:</l>
            <l>What's paſt and preſent is the moſt that can</l>
            <l>By all allowed Art be knowne by Man:</l>
            <l>But, what inſuing Fate may or will be,</l>
            <l>Till paſt preuention he can neuer ſee;</l>
            <l>Nor yet know when, or where good hap, or ill</l>
            <l>May raiſe, or caſt him to the Dale, or Hill</l>
            <l>He can but gueſſe at moſt, and who doth ſo,</l>
            <l>He nothing truly, but by gueſſe ſhall know.</l>
            <l>For what of him the Deſtinies decree,</l>
            <l>Becauſe hee's Man, vnknowne muſt euer be,</l>
            <l>Then let not him preſume that's fortunate,</l>
            <l>Since ſtill vncertaine is his doubtfull state.</l>
            <l>Since Pleaſures Syrens are, that Ruine ſing;</l>
            <l>Since Fortunes great doe great misfortunes bring;</l>
            <l>Since there's no Earthly welfare or delight,</l>
            <l>That with the Morne doth riſe, but ſets er'e Night.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:41"/>
            <l>And why through dangers, reſtles cares, and paine,</l>
            <l>Should man attempt fraile honors to obtaine?</l>
            <l>When got, his puft-vp thoughts ſo vainely range,</l>
            <l>That, what they are, and ô! how ſoone they change,</l>
            <l>He cannot thinke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for with a thought they vary,</l>
            <l>So, hopes to hold thoſe haps which cannot tarry.</l>
            <l>And who ſees not, that to none other end</l>
            <l>Fortune doth oft to Man her f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uours lend,</l>
            <l>But, on poore him her Tiranny to try,</l>
            <l>And laugh to ſee him for her liue, and dye.</l>
            <l>For, when in greateſt height of beſt delight,</l>
            <l>In thought ſecure, in honors ſhining bright;</l>
            <l>When rockt, and lul'd in Pleaſures charming lap,</l>
            <l>Scorning to thinke that ought can breed miſhap,</l>
            <l>Fortune, to ſhew her euer-changing power,</l>
            <l>Turnes in a Moment, all his ſweet to ſower,</l>
            <l>And from thoſe deſtin'd Ills, ô how ſhall he</l>
            <l>Poore ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uile bondman manumiſed be?</l>
            <l>To whom ſhall he appeale? or who hath power?</l>
            <l>I'ſt angry Heauen? Fates? Starres? or ſome thing lower?</l>
            <l>Yea, 'tis himſelfe; for he was fram'd by <hi>Ioue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To be all other Creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es far aboue,</l>
            <l>Next to his euer-great all ſeeing Maker,</l>
            <l>Of wiſdome, and ſafe prouidence partaker.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:10"/>
            <l>But he as ſubiect to his ſtraying will,</l>
            <l>En bracing that for good, which tride is ill,</l>
            <l>And weighing not how fraile a thing is man,</l>
            <l>Not yet for eſeeing what Chance hourely can,</l>
            <l>Forgets himſelfe, and without meane, or meaſure,</l>
            <l>Wakes to waſt I me, yet dreames on nought but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</l>
            <l>And, with his faults ſo partially doth beate,</l>
            <l>That vntill ruin'd, cannot Ruine feare.</l>
            <l>He dreads no fire vntill he feele it burne,</l>
            <l>Till whipt with his owne Rods doth neuer turne,</l>
            <l>Then his miſdeeds, and then his Time miſpent,</l>
            <l>With too late penitence he doth lament.</l>
            <l>Thus vnaduiled Neghgence doth bring</l>
            <l>Him to be Sorrones helples vnderling.</l>
            <l>Thus to himſelfe he proues a traiterous foe,</l>
            <l>And Vipe: like is Mother of his woe:</l>
            <l>For, in his breſt hes many a thought, and deed,</l>
            <l>That comming forth, doe his deſtruction breed;</l>
            <l>And man, as fearing he ſhould ſcanted be</l>
            <l>Of his forbid deſtes, ſo eagerly</l>
            <l>Doth all then mottall baites ingurgitate,</l>
            <l>Whe therewith ſhould ne're be ſatiate.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> being once to tunne amiſſe inclin'd,</l>
            <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s he fees not, ſelfe will makes him blind,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>And leades him headlong vnto curſed ends,</l>
            <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he can thinke what danger him attends:</l>
            <l>And now, youth's heedleſſe and vnbridled rage,</l>
            <l>And euen ſome of greene and tender Age.</l>
            <l>Vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cemingly can vaunt how they will drinke,</l>
            <l>Quaffe, and carouſe; and thoſe themſelues doe linke</l>
            <l>With men debauth'd, vile, lauith, and prophane,</l>
            <l>Which worke their owne, and their Aſſociates bane:</l>
            <l>Which, like diſeaſes, doe Society</l>
            <l>Corrupt with their infectious Company:</l>
            <l>Which daily on the vtter Ruine feed</l>
            <l>Of raſh youth, which haue neither head nor heed:</l>
            <l>And thoſe things which for Comforts we ſhould vſe,</l>
            <l>Lake wretches, they vnthankefully abuſe,</l>
            <l>For ſhame, for pitty, for your ſelues forbeare,</l>
            <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ingſters ſly their haunts; the Plague is there.</l>
            <l>Then harmes, are by Examples ſtill reueal'd,</l>
            <l>To <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> we ſee permits them not conceal'd:</l>
            <l>That we may notice take, and ſafely ſhun,</l>
            <l>The dangers which ſo many haue vndone.</l>
            <l>But now our Corne is ouer growne with weed,</l>
            <l>And men euen ſtriue who may in vice exceed.</l>
            <l>The trueſt badge of a true Gallants will,</l>
            <l>Is to be dating in attempting Ill.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>They muſt not ſeeme their Vaniues to hide,</l>
            <l>But mount the Pitch where moſt they may be ſpide:</l>
            <l>I or they are growne to ſuch a monſtrous height,</l>
            <l>In all they euen glory to delight.</l>
            <l>They with braue outward ſhews much baſeneſſe hide,</l>
            <l>And fly aloft with wings of towring pride:</l>
            <l>They tage; and quench with blood hot Angers fires,</l>
            <l>And coole with Sin their heate of lewd deſires,</l>
            <l>Or lewd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es, begot of Fancies foule,</l>
            <l>That tune health, and wealth, and wit, and Soule.</l>
            <l>Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to themſelues, Sinnes very lees,</l>
            <l>And po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoned ſweetes, ſtolne from forbidden Trees,</l>
            <l>The fearefull acts of blacke and ſhameleſſe Night,</l>
            <l>Honey for Drones, for D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uells the delight,</l>
            <l>And we (too true) doe by Experience ſee,</l>
            <l>That great and ſmall by them ſtill ruin'd be.</l>
            <l>It is not powe, or golden Vanity,</l>
            <l>Still blinding I une, or maskt Hypocriſie,</l>
            <l>Or making Iuſtice from her limns ſtray</l>
            <l>Can ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e theſe crimes, or waſh then ſpots away</l>
            <l>'Twere Sin to thinke ſo for the end it tues,</l>
            <l>When the rewards of Vice are miſeries,</l>
            <l>For come (and none how ſoone know) muſt the time,</l>
            <l>When knowne and pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be euery Caime.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>And thoſe ſweet Sins which did the Senſe delight,</l>
            <l>Shall then their Foſterers with woe, requite.</l>
            <l>The fruit that we by Pleaſures paſt ſhall gaine,</l>
            <l>Will be ſoone ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng ioyes, for laſting paine:</l>
            <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all that we ſhall gaine, will be but this,</l>
            <l>And remembrance, that we did amiſſe,</l>
            <l>For tell you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, chaim'd with vanity,</l>
            <l>And haples wretches with the memory</l>
            <l>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d of woe, and vengeance-crying ins;</l>
            <l>What haue you got? the cheating Diuell wins,</l>
            <l>And ſtaling downe but counte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted pleaſure,</l>
            <l>You to gaine that, doe loſe the priceleſſe treaſure</l>
            <l>Of all your grace, your liberty, and bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le,</l>
            <l>And he gets by your wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll folly this.</l>
            <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto your ſelues, for your owne ſake,</l>
            <l>For iuſt accompt you for your ſelue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt make.</l>
            <l>Recall your thoughts, each fond deſire ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey,</l>
            <l>And their fraile motions euer diſobey:</l>
            <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pend not Time, and ſpoyle not ſtower of youth,</l>
            <l>Belieue not Pleaſure, though her words ſeeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th.</l>
            <l>Due<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your Steps into none other Tract.</l>
            <l>But ſuch as Ve tue treds in ſhew and act.</l>
            <l>That way is ſafe, and neuer leads amiſſe,</l>
            <l>But crownes your Iournies end with endles bliſſe.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>There are no Traps, there none will you betray,</l>
            <l>No Wolues on haimeles I ambes there dare to prey.</l>
            <l>Your Guidreſſe here, whilſt you with her doe goe,</l>
            <l>Warrants your ſafety 'gainſt your greateſt Foe:</l>
            <l>And no deuice can make her falſe to thoſe,</l>
            <l>Which confidence in her defence repoſe.</l>
            <l>What ſhe doth game, whilſt you with her doe liue,</l>
            <l>The profit freely ſhe to you will giue:</l>
            <l>She will your Cauſe 'gainſt all the world maintaine</l>
            <l>And neuer ſhame you: but you friends ſhall gaine</l>
            <l>Of all good Men; and ſuch as run aſtray</l>
            <l>Sha l curſe the Time, they follow'd not your way</l>
            <l>And of your goodneſſe, to Poſterity,</l>
            <l>When dead, you leaue ſhall happy memory.</l>
            <l>Next doe not Parents wary Counſell ſlight,</l>
            <l>Nor make not of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue friends aduiſings light:</l>
            <l>Faults which you ſee not, nor of them be told</l>
            <l>By your Companions, they with griefe behold,</l>
            <l>And oft what deere expetience them hath bought,</l>
            <l>You may both heare, and learne, and ſhun for nought.</l>
            <l>And then, leaſt like a muddy poole that ſtandeth ſtill,</l>
            <l>Filth ſelfe your body, and corrupt your will,</l>
            <l>In ſome good action euer buſied be,</l>
            <l>So ne're corrupting Idleneſſe ſhall ſee</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>A banefull Oportunity, to draw</l>
            <l>Your weakenes to infringe the ſacred Law</l>
            <l>Of heauenly Vertue, whom the Gods muſt right,</l>
            <l>Maugre all-horrid Hell's infernall might.</l>
            <l>And be of Company moſt circumſpect,</l>
            <l>That you may good in brace, and bad reiect:</l>
            <l>That with good liquor, your new Veſſells may</l>
            <l>At firſt be fill'd, that ſtill a taſt may ſtay,</l>
            <l>Leſt that the Bud in comming forth be blaſted,</l>
            <l>And ſo the fruit be all vntimely waſted.</l>
            <l>Then your minds forces muſter, Sin to foile,</l>
            <l>Proclaime Defiance, Peace with it is ſpoile:</l>
            <l>If you want aid, and dare not breake the Truce,</l>
            <l>Vertue will help to ruine Times abuſe:</l>
            <l>And Vice, flee, when Vertue doth appeare,</l>
            <l>Like Thieues, that puniſhment of Iuſtice feare.</l>
            <l>O, thinke on this, and know that if you fight</l>
            <l>With Vice, by Vertue, till you kill it quite,</l>
            <l>Celeſtiall Bliſſe your Victory ſhall crowne,</l>
            <l>And trecherous Vice, with Ruine ſhall come downe.</l>
            <l>For Time will all deſtroy that Time miſpend,</l>
            <l>Then weigh your follies, and in time amend.</l>
            <l>A Sigh here ſtopt the paſſage of his breath,</l>
            <l>Whilſt in his lookes appeared meagre death:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>And as an outward Signe of inward woe,</l>
            <l>He ſmote his Breſt, while Teares did ouerfloe,</l>
            <l>Then ſeem'd his lookes, and lift-vp hands to ſay,</l>
            <l>Take heed by me, ſo vaniſht he away.</l>
            <l>Whereat ſuch paſſion did aſſaile my heart,</l>
            <l>That I from Sleepe, amazed, vp did ſtart.</l>
            <l>But what this Dreame pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag'd I could not gueſſe,</l>
            <l>Or if I could, I cannot well expreſſe:</l>
            <l>For vari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us thoughts, had Arguments ſo many,</l>
            <l>That I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unded, vnderſtood not any.</l>
            <l>Till, after, viewing Londons ſtately Streets,</l>
            <l>Wherein the Streame of Vanity ſtill fleets;</l>
            <l>And ſwiftly runs away, as hauing beene</l>
            <l>Ne're there at all; that more may ſtill be ſeene.</l>
            <l>Then, what I ſleeping did but ſeeme to ſee,</l>
            <l>There, there, I waking found too true to be.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>DESERTS COMPLAINT.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LAte, wandting by a Valley ſide,</l>
               <l>Where weeping Streames did ſadly glide,</l>
               <l>Sith <hi>Soll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> bright Raies could not appeare,</l>
               <l>The place, or ought therein to cheare,</l>
               <l>I ſaw clad in a mourning Weed</l>
               <l>A Man whoſe griefes, my griefe did breed.</l>
               <l>For Deſa t deſert there (alas)</l>
               <l>Vpon his Brow ingrauen was,</l>
               <l>And coldly on cold Earth he lay</l>
               <l>Like ſome fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d picture of Decay.</l>
               <l>Or like an ancient Monument,</l>
               <l>Which was erected, to preuent</l>
               <l>Th'obliuion of ſome noble fact:</l>
               <l>Which, ſome dead Worthy once did act;</l>
               <l>And being ruin'd, would inforce</l>
               <l>All the ſpectators with remorce</l>
               <l>To breath forth helples ſighes; and then</l>
               <l>To r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile on Time, and check thoſe men</l>
               <l>That let Decay to diſinherit</l>
               <l>True Worth of what it had by Merit.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Thus did he lye, and like a Swan</l>
               <l>Dying, to eaſe his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t began</l>
               <l>In ſad laments to ſing his woe,</l>
               <l>And thus he ſighing on did goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where ſhall I runne? where ſhall I fly?</l>
               <l>Where ſhall my plaints find remedy?</l>
               <l>Where are mine ancient friends? and where</l>
               <l>My followers that held me deare?</l>
               <l>Where may my now-loſt honors be?</l>
               <l>Where is the Time that fauour'd me?</l>
               <l>And where and how, and what am I</l>
               <l>That in this wretched State here lye?</l>
               <l>Of former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyes am I not reft?</l>
               <l>And of the careles World quite left?</l>
               <l>Are not my followers diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dain'd, diſpis'd, poore, and oppreſt?</l>
               <l>Are not my chiefeſt friends all dead?</l>
               <l>Are not many honors from me fled?</l>
               <l>And is not ſtrangely Time diſguis'd?</l>
               <l>O yes, for by it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me deſpis'd.</l>
               <l>I am an out-caſt, and dejected,</l>
               <l>And ſee with griefe my Rites neglected:</l>
               <l>And many doe vſurpe my place</l>
               <l>Which me, themſelues, and it deface,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And vnto ſuch, I plainely ſee,</l>
               <l>The world doth giue what's due to me,</l>
               <l>If men diſpiſe, and ſlight me ſo,</l>
               <l>I cannot thinke where I may goe.</l>
               <l>And what to doe, I know not, I,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe, I ceaſe to be; and dye.</l>
               <l>I am not franticke, for I know</l>
               <l>By ſad Experience of my woe,</l>
               <l>My hapleſſe words are too too true.</l>
               <l>Which they I feare too ſoone will rue,</l>
               <l>If to the Country I retire,</l>
               <l>There dull and earthly minds require</l>
               <l>Houſes, and Acres, by which now</l>
               <l>Deſert is meaſur'd, therefore how</l>
               <l>Can I, whom Fate hath ſeem'd t'ordaine,</l>
               <l>This Reputations want to plaine,</l>
               <l>And all fraile outwards but to ſlight,</l>
               <l>Of them craue fauour, much leſſe right?</l>
               <l>Of my Complaints, and wrongs appeaſe,</l>
               <l>Since dull-beſotting Error theſe</l>
               <l>Doth ſo much blind, that they ſcarſe ſee</l>
               <l>The odds betweene the Droane and Bee?</l>
               <l>And yet, if good on Earth doe dwell</l>
               <l>'Tis in a ſimple ruſtickes Cell.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>But let me wander in the Citty,</l>
               <l>O! both to her, and gentle pitty,</l>
               <l>I am a ſtranger, and find none</l>
               <l>To entertaine me; but alone</l>
               <l>I through her babling ſtreets doe paſſe,</l>
               <l>That cry, What lacke ye? when (alaſſe)</l>
               <l>Though I what ſhe hath lacke, and ſhe</l>
               <l>Be poore in what abounds in me,</l>
               <l>And each might other gladly pleaſure,</l>
               <l>For each doth want the others treaſure:</l>
               <l>Yet ſhe, (as 'tis the vſe) affecting</l>
               <l>Onely her ſelfe; and me reſpecting</l>
               <l>But like vnto commodities</l>
               <l>Not vendable; am of no price.</l>
               <l>Thus her wiſe Ignorance doth ſlight me:</l>
               <l>And ne're, I feare, will learne to right me.</l>
               <l>And when the ſtately Court I view,</l>
               <l>Whoſe glitting, and whoſe ſun-like hew</l>
               <l>Dazles the Eyes of euery Wight</l>
               <l>That wants a Princelike Eagles ſight;</l>
               <l>There I lye clouded, and this brightneſſe</l>
               <l>May not reflex on me it's lightneſſe.</l>
               <l>I am obſcure, and was not taught</l>
               <l>To ſooth, or by him to be laught,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſees me ſtriue to gaine eſteeme,</l>
               <l>And not to be what I would ſeeme.</l>
               <l>I cannot brauing looke, and be</l>
               <l>One, into whom could men but ſee,</l>
               <l>They might all baſeneſſe there behold,</l>
               <l>Yet thoſe, then Impudence more bold,</l>
               <l>Can looke, and vildely will aſſume</l>
               <l>To them great matters; and preſume,</l>
               <l>When all their Fortunes doe depend</l>
               <l>On others, and with others end.</l>
               <l>Yet ſometimes in the Court I liue,</l>
               <l>But want, and therefore none will giue.</l>
               <l>From hence, if to the Campe I goe,</l>
               <l>There's nothing now for me to doe.</l>
               <l>For iuſly Peace, although it pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And in the end muſt Warre appeaſe,</l>
               <l>Yet ſo it iniures Armes and me,</l>
               <l>That to my face, and griefe I ſee</l>
               <l>The Campe's a Market place, or Faire,</l>
               <l>Where all to buy and ſell, repaire.</l>
               <l>Deſert gets nothing, not a friend</l>
               <l>That might, as 'tis the faſhion, ſend</l>
               <l>A letter of Commends to any,</l>
               <l>That without me, preferreth many.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Thus all my friends, I feare will fly me,</l>
               <l>Sith, now they get ſo little by me.</l>
               <l>Yet ſince the Campe, Court, Countrey, Citty,</l>
               <l>Will not my caſe, I theirs doe pitty.</l>
               <l>O! I ſo poore, and meane am deem'd,</l>
               <l>With few I liue, of few eſteem'd:</l>
               <l>I had a Time, but now (alaſſe)</l>
               <l>I can but boaſt that once I was.</l>
               <l>O! once I was, now to my griefe,</l>
               <l>I cannot be, I want reliefe.</l>
               <l>Yet once I ioyd a States-mans Seate,</l>
               <l>And ſuch men onely I, made great.</l>
               <l>And ô how bright ſhin'd then their Fame,</l>
               <l>Which, well agreed with place and name:</l>
               <l>For then without Deſert not any</l>
               <l>Could riſe; though now I feare too many.</l>
               <l>When Fathers by my helpe had wonne,</l>
               <l>Honor, and Fame: yet if the Sonne,</l>
               <l>Did onely houſe, and name inherit,</l>
               <l>And by Deſert did nothing merit,</l>
               <l>Thoſe illegitmate were deem'd,</l>
               <l>And for their greatneſſe leſſe eſteem'd.</l>
               <l>Twas not, (ô happy then) as now</l>
               <l>When a vild i'eaſant for the Plow,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And nought elſe fit, yoakes thee Deſert,</l>
               <l>And ſeruile makes which free borne wert.</l>
               <l>For his blind earthy mind can ſee</l>
               <l>No happineſſe more, then to be</l>
               <l>Bleſt, (as he thinkes) with pretious gold,</l>
               <l>For which he findes is bought and ſold</l>
               <l>All honors, titles, all Earths bliſſes,</l>
               <l>Which are the period of his wiſhes.</l>
               <l>But for the high Contents of mind,</l>
               <l>Their Heauen, his groſeneſſe cannot finde:</l>
               <l>Yet this is he whom moſt men hold</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n; a man worth gold.</l>
               <l>This muſt Authority poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>That others faults he may redreſſe,</l>
               <l>But knowes not how: and why ſhould he</l>
               <l>Blind in his owne, anothers ſee?</l>
               <l>Alaſſe he doth vſurp his place,</l>
               <l>And all the Rues thereof deface:</l>
               <l>But, ſith by me, men ſhould obtaine it,</l>
               <l>If they without me might not gaine it,</l>
               <l>Then reaſon would force ſome to proue me,</l>
               <l>And prouing, all would better loue me.</l>
               <l>Beſides, preferments would attend</l>
               <l>On me that I might be the end,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Whereat Mens wronged thoughts might aime;</l>
               <l>And ſo a world of faults reclaime.</l>
               <l>For I ne're vndertooke that thing</l>
               <l>That fail'd a bleſt reward to bring;</l>
               <l>Though now to ill, by Times blind Error</l>
               <l>The good is turn'd for all Times terror.</l>
               <l>Ah, once without me none aſpir'd,</l>
               <l>For I in greatnes was requir'd;</l>
               <l>Which as it ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed me to gaine,</l>
               <l>So downe on it the Heauens did raine</l>
               <l>Showers of honor, that ſtill greene,</l>
               <l>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant, and growing it was ſeene:</l>
               <l>And then all ſuch as me neglected</l>
               <l>Could neuer ri e but were defected.</l>
               <l>But then I was ſo lou'd, that he</l>
               <l>Was happy, which could follow me.</l>
               <l>Sometimes my Studies were deuine,</l>
               <l>Wherein deepe knowledge made me ſhine.</l>
               <l>I was a Shepheard, and did keepe</l>
               <l>Free from the Fox and Wolfe my Sheepe:</l>
               <l>But now my Flocke is lur'd from me,</l>
               <l>And Droanes ſucke honey from the Bee.</l>
               <l>Parnaſſus Mount I did frequent,</l>
               <l>And with the ſacred Muſes ſpent</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Labour, and Time: they kind, and free</l>
               <l>From their owne ſelues did giue to me.</l>
               <l>But they their bleſt guifts, ſo deuin'd,</l>
               <l>That onely they inricht the mind.</l>
               <l>And poore my Body was; and when</l>
               <l>I ſought reliefe for it of men,</l>
               <l>My wants were laught at, made a ſcorne,</l>
               <l>And I, in my diſtreſſe forlorne.</l>
               <l>And ſtill I ſaw, and wept to ſee</l>
               <l>How Fortune alwaies ran from me,</l>
               <l>Who, with much Care and Labour, ſought her,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thoſe that for her look'd not, caught her.</l>
               <l>O 'tis decreed, for ſuch is Fate,</l>
               <l>And ſuch a Schollers iniur'd ſtate.</l>
               <l>I tedious Trauells did indure,</l>
               <l>To make my vnderſtanding ſure,</l>
               <l>And others woes haue ſeene and knowne,</l>
               <l>That I might better ſhun mine owne:</l>
               <l>Yea, forraigne Tongues and manners gain'd,</l>
               <l>And deare Experience I obtain'd;</l>
               <l>Yet, home-ſpun Clownes before me farre,</l>
               <l>By Times abuſe preferred are.</l>
               <l>When I returne from bloody warres,</l>
               <l>With feebled Limbes, with wounds, and ſcarres,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Which, for but Truth, and Honors ſake,</l>
               <l>My prime of yeares did vndertake.</l>
               <l>Yet if with odious want diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>So ſlighted, and ſo vnredreſt,</l>
               <l>It thouſands would inforce to ſweare,</l>
               <l>Deſert muſt out of faſhion weare:</l>
               <l>And out of faſhion, who'le reſpect it?</l>
               <l>All will for faſhions ſake neglect it:</l>
               <l>This Age is blind, it cannot ſee</l>
               <l>The ſweet Content <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hid in me.</l>
               <l>It thinkes not how my Seruants haue,</l>
               <l>Which follow'd me, now dead in Graue,</l>
               <l>Still liuing honors, and lou'd Fame,</l>
               <l>That both Poſterity and name</l>
               <l>Crownes with Obſeruance and regard,</l>
               <l>Such is Deſerts allow'd Reward.</l>
               <l>But Tune and Error now contend,</l>
               <l>My Dues and Rights from me to rend:</l>
               <l>Preferment now from me is fled,</l>
               <l>Which me as Husband once did wed,</l>
               <l>And would not lend a glance to any</l>
               <l>But onely Me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet now to many</l>
               <l>So common, like baſe Strumpets growne</l>
               <l>That all for Coyne make them the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> owne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And ſtill-ſought Oportunity,</l>
               <l>My once preuailing friend, ô why</l>
               <l>Doſt thou of help and fauour reaue me,</l>
               <l>And me in my diſtreſſe thus leaue me?</l>
               <l>I ne're did thee neglect, or euer</l>
               <l>Did thee from my Achiuements ſeuer:</l>
               <l>But begg'd thy happy aid. But ſure</l>
               <l>Corruption now doth thee allure.</l>
               <l>Thus am I wrong'd, diſgrac'd, defam'd,</l>
               <l>And yet the world is not aſham'd</l>
               <l>To ſee how moſt vniuſtly I</l>
               <l>The aime am made of iniury.</l>
               <l>Yet I ne're ſham'd, or wrongd this Land,</l>
               <l>But for her honors firme doe ſtand:</l>
               <l>I ne're did ſeeke to waſt her ſtore,</l>
               <l>But was the meane to make it more.</l>
               <l>I ne're was falſe, fond, or vniuſt,</l>
               <l>I ne're with ſelfe-conſuming Luſt,</l>
               <l>Was to my Country blot, or ſtaine,</l>
               <l>Nor Fame on me had cauſe to plaine.</l>
               <l>No mifchiefe I did act, or plot,</l>
               <l>And States abuſer I am not:</l>
               <l>No Innocent I ere accus'd,</l>
               <l>And no iniuſtice euer vs'd.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>I ne're with bribes was hir'd, or bought,</l>
               <l>Not I Authority e're brought</l>
               <l>Deſertleſly to leaſt diſgrace,</l>
               <l>By wronging her moſt ſacred place.</l>
               <l>Nor am I plague of State, or power,</l>
               <l>And yet my Starres on me doe lower.</l>
               <l>I no blaſpheming Roarer was,</l>
               <l>No Bruers beaſt, good-fellow-Aſſe.</l>
               <l>No bragadochio-brauing-Mate,</l>
               <l>No Swaſher, no Repent-too-late:</l>
               <l>No griefe of Reaſon, Ape of pride,</l>
               <l>No ſhadow, but a ſubſtance tride.</l>
               <l>O! I was neuer ought that's vile,</l>
               <l>Nor any euer did beguile.</l>
               <l>I was plaine-dealing, and did fly</l>
               <l>All cauſes of indignity:</l>
               <l>I was not pitch that ſtill defiles</l>
               <l>The toucher, I was free from guiles.</l>
               <l>My followers yet could neuer ſay,</l>
               <l>I lead them wrong, or to decay.</l>
               <l>Yet at the loweſt Ebbe am I</l>
               <l>Of Want, and ſcorned miſery.</l>
               <l>O! tis my Fate, I may not thriue,</l>
               <l>Or bring home honey to the hiue.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And why? I am not eminent,</l>
               <l>Nor Princes Palaces frequent:</l>
               <l>Nor am I complementall matter,</l>
               <l>But hate to temporiſe and flatter.</l>
               <l>I am not like the Apes of Time,</l>
               <l>That often for a downefall climbe;</l>
               <l>I reſt content, and ſtriue t'auoid</l>
               <l>Ambition, that is ſtill imploid</l>
               <l>In her owne ruine; and doth gaine</l>
               <l>Nothing but trouble for her paine.</l>
               <l>For ſhadowes I doe neuer ſtriue,</l>
               <l>But am alaſſe too good to thriue.</l>
               <l>I coſen none, nor haue deceits,</l>
               <l>Nor can I fiſh with golden baites:</l>
               <l>With golden baites, that too too much</l>
               <l>Inſnare all thoſe, that them but touch.</l>
               <l>And right, or wrong are ſought for, when</l>
               <l>They draw like Loadſtones Iron-men,</l>
               <l>They doe corrupt, and alwaies where</l>
               <l>Man goes, he findes Corruption there:</l>
               <l>For wer't not ſo; and if exil'd</l>
               <l>Were fauour, that alaſſe doth ſhield</l>
               <l>Deſertleſſe Vpſtarts; onely rais'd</l>
               <l>That greatneſſe might not ſtill be prais'd;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Then well-deſeruers well regarded</l>
               <l>Would be; the ill, as ill rewarded.</l>
               <l>And men in nought, but doing well</l>
               <l>Would ſtriue each other to excell,</l>
               <l>And in mine ancient honors I</l>
               <l>Should be inſtall'd, and mount on high,</l>
               <l>I Time ob'curely ſhould not ſpend,</l>
               <l>But whom I ſerue ſhould me attend,</l>
               <l>And Ignorance ſhould neuer bring</l>
               <l>Deſert to be her Vnder ing:</l>
               <l>Her vnderling that ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth low,</l>
               <l>Lake obſcure Shrubs; yet when winds blow</l>
               <l>Are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>afe, whileſt euery ſtormy gale</l>
               <l>Shakes lofty Cedars till they fall.</l>
               <l>Then Worldlings come, and loue, and try,</l>
               <l>My bliſſe: I giue ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urity</l>
               <l>To all my Creditors; that neuer</l>
               <l>Deſert ſhall faile, till Time diſſeuer</l>
               <l>Iuſtice, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an: and Wiſdome power</l>
               <l>Wants; while the Heauens for it lower.</l>
               <l>And thou Occaſion g aunt thus much,</l>
               <l>I may no more thy baldneſſe touch;</l>
               <l>O let me come before, that I</l>
               <l>May but thy lucky fore-locke ſpy,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And I'le catch at it faſt; if not</l>
               <l>(As now) let me be ſtill forgot.</l>
               <l>And come you mentall Vertues all</l>
               <l>Saue me, leſt you your ſelues doe fall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>You are defended, you reuiue</l>
               <l>Onely, by keeping me aliue.</l>
               <l>And <hi>ALBION</hi> to thee I cry,</l>
               <l>Saue me for thy neceſſity.</l>
               <l>And Greatneſſe doe thou fauour me,</l>
               <l>Then I againe my friends ſhall ſee.</l>
               <l>Thou m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k'ſt, or marr'ſt, then grace me ſo,</l>
               <l>That I for thee may greater grow:</l>
               <l>But if thou ſlightſt me, and deny</l>
               <l>To doe me right; know I muſt dye,</l>
               <l>That all the Land may mourne for me,</l>
               <l>That, ſeruilizd, firſt made it free.</l>
               <l>Thus ſaid, and being not imploid</l>
               <l>In ought, that might dead Sleepe avoid</l>
               <l>Forthwith a Drouſie ſlumber ſei'd</l>
               <l>His ſenſes, and his moanes appeas'd,</l>
               <l>And, as of Mans ſociety</l>
               <l>The ſlighted outcaſt he did lye.</l>
               <l>When, loc, a Virgin did ariſe</l>
               <l>From Earth; whom neuer mortall Eies</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Beheld; or was by memory</l>
               <l>Recorded, to be noted by:</l>
               <l>Thought knew her not, ſhe could be found</l>
               <l>No where, till now, but vnder ground.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>OBLIVION</hi> was her diſmall name,</l>
               <l>Whom all the World may iuſtly blame:</l>
               <l>For, ſoone ſhe laid (ô dire miſhap!)</l>
               <l>Deſert vpon her fable lap.</l>
               <l>There ſhe (alaſſe) in ſilent ſleep</l>
               <l>Him from the blinded world doth keep.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Put ſtay, awake, awake Deſert!</l>
               <l>We cannot ſay thou onely wert.</l>
               <l>We dare not thinke ſo, and much leſſe,</l>
               <l>Belieue we are in ſuch diſtreſſe:</l>
               <l>Except we with conceipt would all</l>
               <l>Deſpaire, and hopeleſſe with thee fall.</l>
               <l>But aged Heauens in their care</l>
               <l>To vs and thee more gratious are:</l>
               <l>For thou art not of all friends reſt,</l>
               <l>Nor maiſt thou of thy friends be left.</l>
               <l>He that the Scepter of this land</l>
               <l>Doth ſway, and nought but right command,</l>
               <l>Hath place, and being for thee; where</l>
               <l>He thee and thine expects; and there</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Thy followers are onely plac'd:</l>
               <l>And onely by him for thee grac'd.</l>
               <l>And though ſome ſhameleſſe doe intrude,</l>
               <l>Which neuer were with thee indude;</l>
               <l>Know that the glorious Sunne diſplaies</l>
               <l>On all things his reuiuing Raies:</l>
               <l>And to each Creature which doth liue,</l>
               <l>He the beſt nouriſhment doth giue,</l>
               <l>He ſhines vpon the ſweeteſt flowers,</l>
               <l>Which flouriſh in the choiſeſt bowers:</l>
               <l>Yet he alaſſe, can ſhine no where,</l>
               <l>But lurking weeds will ſtart vp there.</l>
               <l>Thou then Deſert art not forlorne,</l>
               <l>Though weeds ſometimes o'regrowne the Corne.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE of a womans Properties, betweene an old man <hi>and a young.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>IF gray Experience may deſerue beliefe,</l>
               <l>Ile tell what Women are; (although with griefe.)</l>
               <l>They and their beauties are ſo vaine and fraile,</l>
               <l>That with their deareſt friends they moſt doe faile.</l>
               <l>And their quaint Trickes doe ſo our Iudgements blind,</l>
               <l>Their guiles we neuer ſee, yet euer finde.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Muſt you ſo hardly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt faire women ſpeake,</l>
               <l>Becauſe (alaſſe) then gentle ſex is weake,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eele not then frath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es burden they, vnleſſe</l>
               <l>We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d with their vnhappineſſe?</l>
               <l>And though they haue ſome poore ſhifts, men haue many:</l>
               <l>And too much would deceaue them without any.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Woman to ſhew, what ſhe would be, at firſt</l>
               <l>Made by her frailty, all the world accurſt.</l>
               <l>And that by her (ſure us by Fate concluded)</l>
               <l>Man ſhalbe euer, as at firſt, deluded.</l>
               <l>Then would all ſeeming Heauen, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d but allot</l>
               <l>That onely man might be, and woman not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>For what ſhe did, grieue more, then blame. Alaſſe,</l>
               <l>His fatall ſubtilty, by which ſhe was</l>
               <l>Vnhappily beguil'd was ſuch, that ſhe</l>
               <l>By it, if man by her, ſoone guil'd might be.</l>
               <l>Yet Heauen this priuiledge doth women giue,</l>
               <l>The world without them ſtands not, nor men liue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Yea, woman ſtill remaines our fatall curſe,</l>
               <l>And will all Vanities for euer nurſe:</l>
               <l>She rebell is to reaſon; yet in wiles</l>
               <l>So witty, that ſhe wiſeſt men beguiles,</l>
               <l>For ſhe is ſuch a ſtrange bewitching thing</l>
               <l>Man muſt her honey haue, though with't a ſting.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>To be our helpes they are, and we doe finde,</l>
               <l>Beauty hath made them louely, Nature kinde;</l>
               <l>And Vertue being female cannot chuſe</l>
               <l>But ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red guift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in her owne Sex infuſe:</l>
               <l>And their faults cannot be ſo much their owne,</l>
               <l>As tempting mans, if all were rightly knowne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>To gaine their owne wils, pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngly they flatter,</l>
               <l>To gather looſe loue, they light lookes can ſcatter:</l>
               <l>O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they to ruine ſweetly can allure,</l>
               <l>And are as luſtfull, as in loue vnſure.</l>
               <l>To where may n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w <hi>Penelope</hi> be found,</l>
               <l>That chaſt was tempted: ſhe is vnder ground.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>She was; and being gone, we ſtill haue new</l>
               <l>Which are, diſpight all falſe ſeducements, true.</l>
               <l>And know this pretty family of Loue</l>
               <l>Are in affection as the turtle Doue.</l>
               <l>Neuer alone, but with vs, and about vs,</l>
               <l>And out of queſtion dye they would without vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>They ſport, and toy, diſſemble, craue, and faine:</l>
               <l>Then frowne, then rage, then hate, and then diſdaine.</l>
               <l>And can ſeeme kinde, where moſt vnkind they proue;</l>
               <l>Yet ſeld or neuer know whom beſt they loue:</l>
               <l>For though they chance with their owne choice to wed,</l>
               <l>Yet, <hi>Venus</hi> muſt haue <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Vulcans</hi> Bed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Yong Man.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ld they we e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inty, or remorceleſſe, then</l>
               <l>They ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> would vnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e the wrongs of men.</l>
               <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed by thoſe,</l>
               <l>In whom th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idence, and tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> repoſe.</l>
               <l>But they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and are ſo kind</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſily th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e yeelding ſoules doe blind.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inded are, and ne're will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe be:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rotten find,</l>
               <l>And yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> inchanting features,</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them. O b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>witching creature.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>How we, ſith they the weaker Veſſels are,</l>
               <l>To tirannize no forged ſlanders ſpare.</l>
               <l>And yet (ſo charitable is their loue)</l>
               <l>They cannot from vs their affections moue.</l>
               <l>Then leaue, if not for ſhame, for pitty, thus</l>
               <l>To wrong them, if they erre, it is for vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Although they ſeeme vs onely to affect,</l>
               <l>'Tis their content, not ours, that they reſpect:</l>
               <l>They for their owne ends cunningly can f ine,</l>
               <l>And though they hau't by natu e, yet theile ſtraine.</l>
               <l>Sure if on Faith by wiles gain'd might be bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Straight that I were a woman I would wiſh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Yong Man.</speaker>
               <l>Alaſſe from ſubtilty ſo farre they are</l>
               <l>That me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eaſily) doe them inſnare:</l>
               <l>And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue; we too often ſee,</l>
               <l>They but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gentle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elues to coſen be.</l>
               <l>But they would all be ſpotleſſe, did men leaue</l>
               <l>Their pittying hearts with fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehood to deceaue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>They are ſo fond, that being flatter'd, will</l>
               <l>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ent to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne Infamy and ill,</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rets vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edly reuea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>And not ſo much as then ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thoughts conceale.</l>
               <l>Yet they though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ttings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe beguile them ſtill,</l>
               <l>Thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flatterers make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooles, and euer will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>When men faire ſpeeches vſe, but to deceaue,</l>
               <l>Wiſe women them of their intents bereaue:</l>
               <l>And thoſe which nought ſuſpect, they doe inſnare,</l>
               <l>And ſuch ſtill wrong'd for well-belieuing are.</l>
               <l>Yet men ſo ſhameleſſe be, that for the ſame</l>
               <l>Whereof themſelues are cauſe; they women blame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Women, when as they liſt, denialls haue;</l>
               <l>Yea oft when to betray themſelues they craue.</l>
               <l>For where's the <hi>Phoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or the ſable Swan,</l>
               <l>Mirror of women, wonder vnto Man,</l>
               <l>But change of paſture greedy is to try,</l>
               <l>And of ſtolne Sin, craues ſtill Variety.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Sith thou are wither'd, and thy blood is cold,</l>
               <l>And haſt no priuiledge to loue, being old,</l>
               <l>Thy doating weakenes enuies thoſe that may,</l>
               <l>Allow'd by youth, with louely <hi>Venus</hi> play.</l>
               <l>But do not hinder them of licenc'd Time,</l>
               <l>Since 'tis but ſhort, and naturall the Crime.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>How counterfeit delights doe blind the Senſe</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e with Folly to diſpence!</l>
               <l>Ah I doe know, which would I neuer had</l>
               <l>Women are all, (I feare to ſay how) bad.</l>
               <l>What iuſtly men deſerue that them belieue;</l>
               <l>The very thought thereof doth make me grieue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Speake on; and if their tempted faults be knowne</l>
               <l>To be leſſe mans prouoking then their owne;</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le yeeld: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd euen blame them cauſe I ſee</l>
               <l>They ſo full of delight, and beauty be.</l>
               <l>And all aduantage of their weakeneſſe take;</l>
               <l>But then my ſelfe hard hearted I muſt make.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Like Crocodiles they moue deſtroying pitty;</l>
               <l>They tune like Syrens a ſweet banefull ditty:</l>
               <l>And are forgetfully of ſome commended,</l>
               <l>Onely with their looſe frailty to be friended.</l>
               <l>And their laſciuious ſex haue carefull beene</l>
               <l>But in this onely, to commit vnſcene.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Sith thou art wither<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and thy blood is cold,</l>
               <l>And haſt no priuiledge to loue, being old,</l>
               <l>Thy doating weakenes enuies thoſe that may,</l>
               <l>Allow'd by youth, with louely <hi>Venus</hi> play.</l>
               <l>But do not hinder them of licenc'd Time,</l>
               <l>Since 'tis but ſhort, and naturall the Crime.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>How counterfeit delights doe blind the Senſe</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as dare with Folly to diſpence!</l>
               <l>Ah I doe know, which would I neuer had</l>
               <l>Women are all, (I feare to ſay how) bad.</l>
               <l>What iuſtly men deſerue that them belieue;</l>
               <l>The very thought thereof doth make me grieue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Speake on; and if their tempted faults be knowne</l>
               <l>To be leſſe mans prouoking then their owne;</l>
               <l>Ile yeeld: and euen blame them cauſe I ſee</l>
               <l>They ſo full of delight, and beauty be.</l>
               <l>And all aduantage of their weakeneſſe take;</l>
               <l>But then my ſelfe hard hearted I muſt make.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Like Crocodiles they moue deſtroying pitty:</l>
               <l>They tune like Syrens a ſweet banefull ditty:</l>
               <l>And are forgetfully of ſome commended,</l>
               <l>Onely with their looſe frailty to be friended.</l>
               <l>And there laſciuious ſex haue carefull beene</l>
               <l>But in this onely, to commit vnſeene.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>If that ſome one of them doe tread awry;</l>
               <l>Muſt all be naught? ô iudge it Charity.</l>
               <l>But ſince man-kind is ſubiect to be tempted,</l>
               <l>Then from this Croſſe they cannot be exempted.</l>
               <l>Yet oftentimes, (ſuch abſtinence they haue)</l>
               <l>They can refuſe, what in their hearts they craue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art a woman ſure diſguis'd; if not,</l>
               <l>Nature that thou ſhould eſt be one did allot:</l>
               <l>And then ſome Hagge, that once, one man might be</l>
               <l>That ſpake of women well, hath thus chang'd thee.</l>
               <l>Elſe when for ſuch knowne miſchiefes I them blame,</l>
               <l>Thou ne're wouldſt ſpeak, but hold thy peace for ſhame</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>All know (vnſufferable Man) they are</l>
               <l>For beauty and delight beyond compare.</l>
               <l>For conference ſo full of pleaſing wit,</l>
               <l>For vſe ſo neceſſary, and ſo fit,</l>
               <l>That man without them, can by no meanes be,</l>
               <l>Nor euer will, if he be rul'd by me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Nay ſure theſe neceſſary harmes were fram'd</l>
               <l>That man, as too too heedleſſe might be blam'd.</l>
               <l>His weakneſſe cannot greateſt weakneſſe fly,</l>
               <l>In her ſtrong-drawing fraile ſociety.</l>
               <l>Then happy they, that know what women are,</l>
               <l>But happier, which to know them neuer care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13525:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Young Man.</speaker>
               <l>Old Father, Ile no more with thee contend,</l>
               <l>But muſt confeſſe, as we, ſo they offend.</l>
               <l>Many of them are good, and many ill,</l>
               <l>Yet all in this erre, all muſt haue their will.</l>
               <l>But for your part, doe you the ſtrife here end,</l>
               <l>And for my pray I'le pray they may amend.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO MY WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and ingenious Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Newman,</hi> on his fore-ſayd Booke.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>NEWMAN,</hi> to praiſe thee to thy face, were not</l>
            <l>Friendſhip, but flattery. T' auoyde which Blot,</l>
            <l>My tardy Verſe is placed at the end</l>
            <l>Of all thy Booke: (as if I did commend</l>
            <l>Thee dead, or abſent.) Yet, if this my Verſe</l>
            <l>Had come Before, not Ouer-tâne the Preſſe,</l>
            <l>I had hung (ſuch is thy prouoking wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>)</l>
            <l>My Bayes vp, with the reſt, to ſet thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rth.</l>
            <l>For, this I prophecy: Thine early Fame</l>
            <l>Shall (oldly) proue as New, as (now) thy Name.</l>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Eundem.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>QViſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Nouo, Veteri nullus blanditur amico,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Te (mihi qui Nouus es nomine, fronte ſimul)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Miror, et inuideo. Tibi non (hoc) blandior ipſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum ſic inuidiâ Carmina digna tua.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>G. Parre, in Art: Mag. Ox:</bibl>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:36"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13525:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
